Siqi Wu

Ann Arbor, MI, USA | siqiwu@umich.edu | https://avalanchesiqi.github.io/

RESEARCH SUMMARY

I aim to derive principles for responsible social systems, with my core expertise in large-scale quantitative analysis and collaboration with experts in social science, communication, and political science. I work towards my goal through a variety of methods – from curating unique social media datasets, to modeling collective user behavior, to building algorithmic audits for identifying negative platform effects, to designing and testing new HCI systems.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Consultant | University of Michigan.

2020.09 - present

- ^ Responsibilities equivalent to a research fellow, work conducted remotely due to pandemic.
- Center for Social Media Responsibility. Adviser: Paul Resnick

Projects include (1) measuring cross-partisan discussions on YouTube; (2) characterizing concept difference and (3) quantifying the impacts of annotator demographics in labeling hate, offensive, and toxic social media content; (4) calibrating prevalence estimation methods for online problematic speech; (5) designing effective training procedure for crowdsourced labeling; (6) auditing polarized recommendations in YouTube recommender system.

Research Fellow | Australian National University. Canberra, ACT, Australia

2020.09 - 2021.03

- Computational Media Lab. Adviser: Lexing Xie

Projects include (1) measuring collective human attention across different social platforms; (2) picturing global media consumption during COVID-19.

Software Engineer | MicroStrategy, Inc. Hangzhou, Zhejiang, China

2015.09 - 2016.05

- Big Data Engine team. Built Apache Spark alike engine to process massive data.

Software Developer Intern | Baidu, Inc. Beijing, China

2014.12 - 2015.02

- Baidu Maps team. Developed a tool to collect realtime traffic status.

EDUCATION

Australian National University. Canberra, ACT, Australia

2016.06 - 2020.09

- PhD in Computer Science. Advisers: Lexing Xie and Marian-Andrei Rizoiu
- Thesis: Measuring collective attention in online content: Sampling, engagement, and network effects

University of Melbourne. Melbourne, VIC, Australia

2013.07 - 2015.07

- Master of Information Technology. Adviser: Richard Sinnott
- Thesis: An architecture for big data processing and visualisation of traffic data

Tianjin University. Tianjin, China

2008.09 - 2012.06

- Bachelor of Electronics Engineering. Adviser: Yugong Wu

AWARDS

- AAAI ICWSM Best Paper Finalist '21
- ACM CSCW Best Paper Honorable Mention '19
- Google PhD Fellowship '18

PUBLICATIONS

- * Equal authorship
- 11. ACT: Active crowd training for crowdsourced labeling
 - Wu*, Rajadesingan*, Budak, Garrett, Sude, and Resnick. Under review
- 10. Whose advantage? Measuring attention dynamics across YouTube and Twitter on controversial topics Lee*, **Wu***, Ertugrul*, Lin, and Xie. *ICWSM* '22. Full paper
- 9. Cross-partisan discussions on YouTube: Conservatives talk to liberals but liberals don't talk to conservatives **Wu** and Resnick. *ICWSM* '21. Full paper, **best paper finalist**
- 8. AttentionFlow: Visualising influence in networks of time series Shin*, Tran*, **Wu***, Mathews, Wang, Lyall, and Xie. *WSDM* '21. Demo paper
- 7. Unsupervised cyberbullying detection via time-informed Gaussian mixture model Cheng, Shu, **Wu**, Silva, Hall, and Liu. *CIKM* '20. Full paper
- 6. Variation across scales: Measurement fidelity under Twitter data sampling **Wu**, Rizoiu, and Xie. *ICWSM* '20. Full paper
- 5. Estimating attention flow in online video networks
 - Wu, Rizoiu, and Xie. CSCW '19. Full paper, best paper honorable mention
- 4. How is attention allocated? Data-driven studies of popularity and engagement in online videos **Wu**. *WSDM '19*. Doctoral consortium
- 3. Beyond views: Measuring and predicting engagement in online videos **Wu**, Rizoiu, and Xie. *ICWSM* '18. Full paper
- 2. Will this video go viral? Explaining and predicting the popularity of YouTube videos Kong, Rizoiu, **Wu**, and Xie. WWW '18. Demo paper
- 1. SMASH: A cloud-based architecture for big data processing and visualization of traffic data **Wu**, Morandini, Sinnott. *DSDIS* '15. Full paper

TEACHING

- Teaching assistant in ANU graduate course COMP6490 Document analysis ('17, '18)
- Teaching assistant in ANU undergraduate course COMP1030 Art of computing ('17)

STUDENTS

- Alex Liu (UMich PhD)
- Cai Yang (ANU undergrad)

COMMUNITY SERVICE

- ICWSM '22 Student Volunteer and Scholarship Chair
- Senior program committee: ICWSM ('22)
- Program committee/Reviewer: ICWSM ('17, '18, '21), CSCW ('19-'22), WebSci ('22), ASONAM ('21), WWW ('19, '20), AAAI ('19), ACM TOIS ('20), EPJ Data Science ('21)

MISC.

- Organizing: co-organized the Computational Media Lab winter workshop '19
- Certificates: 16 MOOC courses, e.g., machine learning, social network analysis, algorithms, etc.
- Running: 18 100+km events, 50+ (ultra) marathons finisher, 2:57 marathon